Chapter 2. The carpet bag.
I stuffed a shirt or two into my old carpet bag, tucked it under my arm, and
started for Cape Horn in the Pacific.
Quitting the good city of old Manhattan, I duly arrived in New Bedford. It was a
Saturday night in December. Much was I disappointed upon learning that the
little packet for Nantucket had already sailed, and that no way of reaching that
place would offer till the following Monday, as most candidates for the pains
and penalties of wailing stop at this same New Bedford then to embark on their
voyage, it may as well be related that I, for one, had no idea of so doing, for
my mind was made up to sail in no other than a Nantucket craft, because there
was a fine, boisterous something about everything connected with that famous
old island which amazingly pleased me.
Besides, though New Bedford has of late been gradually monopolizing the business
of whailing, and though in this matter poor old Nantucket is now much behind
her, yet Nantucket was her great original, the tire of this Carthage, the
place where the first dead American whale was stranded. Where else but from
Nantucket did those Aboriginal whalemen, the red men, first sally out in canoes
to give chase to the Leviathan? And where but from Nantucket too, did that
first adventurous little sloop put forth, partly laden with imported
cobblestones, so goes the story, to throw at the whales, in order to
discover when they were nigh enough to risk a harpoon from the bowsprit.
Now having a night, a day, and still another night following before me in New
Bedford, air I could embark for my destined port, it became a matter of
concernment where I was to eat and sleep. Meanwhile, it was a very dubiousl
looking, nay, a very dark and dismal night, bitingly cold and cheerless. I
knew no one in the place. With anxious grapes, I had sounded my pocket and only
brought up a few pieces of silver. So wherever you go, Ishmael, said I to
myself, as I stood in the middle of a dreary street, shouldering my bag, and
comparing the gloom toward the north with the darkness towards the south.
Wherever in your wisdom you may conclude to lodge for the night, my dear Ishmael,
be sure to inquire the price, and don't be too particular.
With halting steps I paced the streets and passed the sign of the cross
tarpoons, but it looked too expensive and jolly there. Further on, from the
bright red windows of the swordfish inn, there came such fervent rays that it
seemed to have melted the packed snow and ice before the house, for everywhere
else the congealed frost lay 10 in thick in a hard asphaltic pavement, rather
weary for me when I struck my foot against the flinty projections, because
from hard, remorseless service the souls of my boots were in a most miserable
plight. Too expensive and jolly again, thought I, pausing one moment to watch
the broad glare in the street and hear the sounds of the tinkling glasses
within. But go on, Ishmael, said I, at last, don't you hear? Get away from
before the door. Your patched boots are stopping the way. So on I went. I now by
instinct followed the streets that took me waterward, for there doubtless were
the cheapest, if not the cheeriest ends.
such dreary streets, blocks of blackness, not houses, on either hand,
and here and there a candle like a candle moving about in a tomb. At this
hour of the night, of the last day of the week, that quarter of the town
proved all but deserted, but presently I came to a smoky light proceeding from a
low, wide building, the door of which stood invitingly open. It had a careless
look, as if it were meant for the uses of the public. So entering, the first
thing I did was to stumble over an ash box in the porch. Ha, thought I. Ha, as
the flying particles almost choked me.
Are these ashes from that destroyed city, Gamora? But the cross tarpoons and
the swordfish, this then must needs be the sign of the trap. However, I picked
myself up and hearing a loud voice within, pushed on and opened a second interior door.
It seemed a great black parliament sitting in Tophett. A hundred black
faces turned round in their rows to peer, and beyond a black angel of doom
was beating a book in the pulpit. It was a negro church, and the preacher's text
was about the blackness of darkness and the weeping and wailing and teeth
nashing there. Ha!" Ishmael muttered eye, backing out, "Wretched
entertainment at the sign of the trap."
Moving on, I at last came to a dim sort of light, not far from the docks, and
heard a forlorn creaking in the air, and looking up, saw a swinging sign over the
door with a white painting on it, faintly representing a tall, straight
jet of misty spray, and these words underneath, "The Spouter Inn. Peter Coffin."
coffin spout. rather ominous in that particular connection, thought I, but it
is a common name in Nantucket, they say, and I suppose this Peter here is an
immigrant from there, as the light looked so dim, and the place for the
time looked quiet enough, and the dilapidated little wooden house itself
looked as if it might have been carted here from the ruins of some burnt
district, and as the swinging sign had a poverty-stricken sort of creek to it, I
thought that here was the very spot for cheap lodgings, and the best of pea coffee.
It was a queer sort of place, a gable-ended old house, one side Paulied
as it were, and leaning over sadly. It stood on a sharp, bleak corner, where
that tempestuous windon kept up a worse howling than ever it did about poor
Paul's tossed craft. Uralon nevertheless is a mighty pleasant zephr to anyone
indoors, with his feet on the hob, quietly toasting for bed.
In judging of that tempestuous wind called Uraladon, says an old writer, of
whose works I possess the only copy extent, it maketh a marvelous difference
whether thou lookst out at it from a glass window where the frost is all on
the outside, or whether thou observest it from that sashless window, where the
frost is on both sides, and of which the white death is the only glaze.
True enough, thought I, as this passage occurred to my mind. Old black letter
thou reasonest well. Yes, these eyes are windows, and this body of mine is the
house. What a pity they didn't stop up the chinks in the crannies, though, and
thrust in a little lint here and there.
But it's too late to make any improvements now. The universe is
finished. The cop stone is on, and the chips were carted off a million years
ago. Poor Lazarus there chattering his teeth against the curbstone for his
pillow and shaking off his tatters with his shiverings. He might plug up both
ears with rags and put a corn cob in his mouth. And yet that would not keep out
the tempestuous uracon. Uraladon says old Dies in his red silken wrapper. He
had a redder one afterwards. Poo poo what a fine frosty night. How Orion
glitters. What northern lights. Let them talk of their oriental summer climbs of
everlasting conservatories. Give me the privilege of making my own summer with
my own coals. But what thinks Lazarus?
Can he warm his blue hands by holding them up to the grand northern lights?
Would not Lazarus rather be in Sumatra than here? Would he not far rather lay
him down lengthwise along the line of the equator? Yeah, ye gods, go down to
the fiery pit itself in order to keep out this frost.
Now that Lazarus should lie stranded there on the curbstone before the door
of Dies, this is more wonderful than that an iceberg should be mored to one
of the Mlokas. Yet Dies himself, he too lives like a zar in an ice palace made
of frozen size, and being president of a temperance society, he only drinks the
tepid tears of orphans.
But no more of this blubbering. Now we are going a whailing, and there is
plenty of that yet to come. Let us scrape the ice from our frosted feet,
and see what sort of a place this spout may be.